A Guide to the J. Calvitt Clarke, Jr. Papers, 1943-1999
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, Washington and Lee University
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
J. Calvitt Clarke, Jr. Papers, 1943-1999
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
MS 016
24 cubic feet and oversize flat storage.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of J. Calvitt Clarke, III.
Biographical/Historical Information
J.(oseph) Calvitt Clarke, Jr.(1920-2004)was educated at the University of Virginia and practiced law in Richmond from 1944-1975. In 1954, he was a Republican candidate for the U.S. Congress. From 1975 until his death, Clarke served as Judge on the U.S. District Court, Eastern District of Virginia. He took senior status in 1991.
Scope and Content
U.S. District Court case files and opinions, both published and unpublished, constitute about half of this collection. Also included are biographical materials, correspondence, subject files, scrapbooks, political memorabilia and artifacts, and photos. Activities of Clarke's father, J. Calvitt Clarke, are documented in the Christian Children's Fund, Inc. & Children, Inc. papers, 1956-1999 found here.
Arrangement
The materials, which have not been fully processed, are arranged by tentative series.
Contents List
- Biographical Materials, 1944-1993 (Carton 1, oversized folder #1 & framed oversized (unboxed))
- Correspondence, 1974, 1980-1982 (Carton 2)
- Subject Files, 1978-1999 (Carton 2-4)
- Speeches, 1976-1990 (Carton 5)
- Case Files
  - Columbus America, 1996 (Carton 6)
  - Hirschfeld, Runnels & Rennegades, c. 1989-1991 (Carton 7)
  - Pearce, 1983 (Carton 8)
  - Sea Hunt, 2001 (Carton 9)
  - Titanic, 2001 (Carton 9-10)
  - Walker, 1985 (Carton 11)
- Opinions(published & unpublished; loose and bound), 1975-1999 (Carton 12-19)
- Christian Children's Fund, Inc. & Children, Inc., 1956-1999 (Carton 20-21)
- Scrapbook and Clippings, 1954, 1971-1973; 1988-1996 (Carton 22-23)
- Political Memorabilia
  - Printed Materials, 1954-1960 (Carton 24)
  - Artifacts, 1948-1960 (Carton 25)
  - Oversized Materials, 1960 & n.d. (Carton 26 & oversize folder #2)
    Richmond Times Dispatch issues, and 1 reel of 16mm motion picture film, Report to the People- no credits, c. 1956. Film extols accomplishments of first Eisenhower administration. Short clip of Clarke campaigning for Republican seat in Congress is inserted near the end of the film. Oversize folder holds posters, bumper stickers and photos.
- Photos
  - Judges and Clerks of the Eastern District Court of Virginia, 1975-1992 & n.d. (Carton 27)
  - Politicians, 1952-1985 (Carton 27 & Oversize Folder 1)
- Certificates of Award, Merit and Membership, 1943-1995 (Carton 27 & Oversize Folder 1)